# **RICHA VERMA**

Software Engineer | Ex-IBM | 919-656-6209

richa.verma.kz@gmail.com| linkedin.com/in/richa-verma | github.com/richa-verma1001 | rverma-portfolio

#### **CAREER PROFILE**

15 years of fullstack software development experience with IBM; 5 years of experience in frontend stack React, Node.js, Worked as a Technical Lead for 3 key projects at IBM; **Awards:** IBM Outstanding Achievement Award, IBM UX Champion Award; **Patent:** Visual Representation of erroneous fields; **Certifications:** PMI Agile Foundations Practitioner

## **EXPERIENCE**

## Senior Software Engineer | Technical Lead | Agile Coach | IBM | Watson

Aug 2015 - Jun 2018

- Led a team of 8 developers for successful delivery of Watson Company Analyzer on IBM Cloud platform.
- Facilitated project planning, collaborating with stakeholders to refine requirements and prioritize product backlog.
- Worked with design for early feedback on wireframes, enhancing UI, leading to higher customer satisfaction.
- Delivered a fully responsive, high performance React application, leveraging Webpack, React, Node.js, Javascript
- Integrated analytics, tracking events, usage & page views, reporting KPIs for actionable insights to stakeholders.
- Utilized docker and kubernetes to containerize applications & orchestrate deployments for scaling.
- Developed features, led daily scrums, conducted sprint planning and retrospectives while continuously collaborating with stakeholders, optimizing team performance and creating a culture of learning and growth.

## Advisory Software Engineer | Technical Lead | Scrum Master | IBM | Connections

Jan 2010 - Aug 2015

- Led a global team of 10 developers, successfully delivering **multiple** product releases for IBM Connections.
- Received Outstanding Achievement Award for leading successful integration of IBM Mail into Connections.
- Managed client crit-sits, driving open issues to closure and ensuring effective stakeholder communication.
- Developed robust RESTful APIs (JAVA), facilitating seamless frontend-backend data exchange and integration.
- Enabled full test coverage (Mocha), automation testing(Selenium) and continuous integration pipelines(Jenkins)
- Enhanced brand and market presence by publishing articles & delivering presentations at yearly IBM Conference.

## Software Engineer | IBM | Lotus Quickr

Oct 2004 - Dec 2010

- Developed Eclipse IDE wizard in Java to generate custom form instances(XML, XFORMS) for mobile rendering.
- Developed customizable product themes and multiple portlet applications using Java, Javascript and Dojo.
- Implemented secure user session & cookie management, optimizing authentication and maintaining statefulness.
- Received UX Champion Award for increased customer satisfaction with continuous stakeholder engagement

FREELANCE July 2018 - June 2023

A career pause for an expat relocation. Repatriated and excited to return to work

- Published 20+ web applications as demonstrated in Portfolio
- Project Game-Hub: Developed a responsive application to allow users to find, sort & filter games. Integrated backend APIs, offline pages, error handling & a reusable HTTP service to retrieve backend data.
- Developed multiple React and vanilla javascript applications: Memory Cards, User lookup, Shopping List
- Implemented CSS projects demonstrating Infinite Scroll, Paging, Responsive Web Design, Photo Gallery
- Completed certifications: React 18; PMI Agile Foundations; Cert Prep: PMI Agile Practitioner
  Tech Stack: React, Javascript, Node.js, HTML, Chakra, CSS

## **SKILLS**

**Technical:** Java, React, Node.js, Javascript, ES6, JSON, HTML, CSS, SASS, Jest, Mocha, Selenium, Webpack, REST, PostgreSQL, MySQL, JIRA, Jenkins, Docker, Kubernetes; **Leadership:** Team Management, Stakeholder Management, Collaboration, Problem Solving, Adaptability, Team Work, Innovation, Agile Methodologies, Scrum, GitHub

## **EDUCATION**

North Carolina State University, Bachelors in Computer Science (Summa Cum Laude)